<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Get Rusty While Building a Database</title>
    <link href="https://nihaocami.github.io/rusty-db/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://nihaocami.github.io/rusty-db" />
    <updated>2024-12-06T10:03:57-08:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Chris A.</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://nihaocami.github.io/rusty-db</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Words That Need To Be Said</title>
        <author>
            <name>Chris A.</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://nihaocami.github.io/rusty-db/test.html"/>
        <id>https://nihaocami.github.io/rusty-db/test.html</id>

        <updated>2024-12-06T08:27:32-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I have a motto. If you want to learn something very well, teach it - Some wise person Well, not exactly mine. But it is something I heard long time ago and it has proven to be true time and time again. So, as much&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I have a motto.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you want to learn something very well, teach it - Some wise person</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well, not exactly mine. But it is something I heard long time ago and it has proven to be true time and time again. So, as much as I am making this as a contribution to Rust and Rust learners, it is also a selfish endeavour to learn more myself.</p>
<p>In this series, I will be making a simple "lite" database like SQLite from scratch. Though I am aiming to build a NoSql version. Building a database is no simple task and it's a project that I am hoping to keep going for years to come.</p>
<p>While doing this, we will be learning things as simple as defining functions in Rust and as advanced as handling multithreading, memory management and more.</p>
<p>I hope you find these posts useful and that it can help you in your journey to becoming Rusty.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
